# **DERICK OLSON-CHAN**



#### ABOUT ME

Writer, Teacher, and Engineer. I love language, software, and creative teams. I bring a grounded presence, deep listening, and clear communication. My approach to work: *Simplify and decide, Start with action, Ask and offer help.* 

My background ranges from Computer Science to Buddhist Studies. Since 2015, I've worked as a Product Engineer in EdTech and eCommerce, taught university courses, and led workshops on Yoga, Meditation, Latte Art, and the Art of Fiction.



### EDUCATION

2020 - 2023

University of Virginia

Master of Fine Arts | Creative Writing

**2011 - 2015** 

University of Pennsylvania
Bachelor of Arts | Computer Science
Bachelor of Arts | East Asian Studies



## SKILLS

- Full Stack Software Engineering
- JavaScript + TypeScript + React + Node
- GraphQL + Ruby on Rails + RESTful APIs
- Product Engineering
  - SEO + Feature testing
  - Accessibility-first development
- Developer Ecosystems
  - Unit + End-to-End Testing
- Documentation (internal + public)
- Demos + Presentations + Workshops
- Pair Programming + Mentorship

#### VOLUNTEER/PART-TIME

- Barista, Enna Chocolate (2022-2023)
- Digital Humanities Assistant, UVA (Summer 2022)
- Poetry + Fiction Judge, Fralin Museum of Art (2020)
- Podcast Host, OpenMeditations.org (2018 2020)
- JavaScript Teacher, CodeNation (2017-2019)
- Yoga Teacher, Yoga Society of SF (2016 2017)



## REFERENCES

(Contact info available upon request)

- Micheline Marcom
   Author | Professor of English, UVA
   Founder + Director, New American Story Project
- Enna Grazier
   Founder + Owner, Enna Chocolate
- Ronald Williams
   Senior Engineer, Amazon
   Former Director of Frontend Engineering, 1stDibs

# 4

## WORK EXPERIENCE

#### 2023-current

#### Software Consultant

- Helping others turn their ideas into web and mobile experiences.
- Serving individual clients and agencies including Art+Logic and Toptal.
- Tech stack: React, React Native, Node, Ruby on Rails.

## 2021-2022

## University Instructor | University of Virginia

- Empowering students to discover what, how, and why they write.
- Taught two (2) semester-long undergraduate English courses in Fiction, Personal Narrative, and Composition.
- Lectured and facilitated craft workshops, covering genres from Marketing Copy to Personal Memoir.

#### 2017-2020

#### Product Engineer, 1stDibs | 1stDibs.com

- JavaScript development on Core Funnel and International Teams for eCommerce platform with 5M+ monthly visitors.
- Built automated translations system for launch of international websites in: Germany, France, & UK.
- Shipped desktop and mobile UX across public-facing website: Landing / Search / Browse / Product / Checkout.
- Technologies: React, Node, GraphQL, SEO+AMP, A/B Testing, i18n, GitHub Integrations, Mobile Web, Server-Side Rendering.

## • 2015-2017

## **Product Engineer, Remind** | Remind.com/chat

- Full Stack development for EdTech messaging platform with 20M+ monthly active users on Web, iOS, and SMS.
- Focus on speed, reliability, and micro-service architecture.
- Shipped full-stack implementations of Web App redesign, Message Reactions, Profile Images, and Announcement database migration.
- Technologies: Go, Ruby on Rails, React, Apollo, Twilio API, CircleCl, PostgreSQL, DynamoDB.

## 2013 - 2015

# Teaching Assistant, University of Pennsylvania

 Weekly talks on Functional Programming (OCaml), Data Structures, Object-Oriented Design (Java), and Theory of Computation (LaTeX).